They called me Lilya Lungina
Between ages five to ten, when I lived in Germany, I was called Lili Markovich
Then, from ten to fourteen, in France, they called me Lilia Markovich
In my mother's puppet show, I was called Lili Imali
Imali is mother's pseudonym, Ancient Hebrew for "my mom"
That's how many names I used to have...
... and just as many schools.
I went to -- I counted once -- twelve different schools
But during this long life -- my birthday will be on July 16 [1997]
It's terrifying. I'd never think that one could live so long
I still haven't gotten used to calling myself by my name and patronym
Nevertheless, seventy-seven years is a lot. And it's time to sum up.
And on the other hand, how do you summarize an activity, a vocation?
How do you summarize life?
I think, that the summary of life is life itself.
All the happy, difficult, miserable, blazing, and faded moments, the collection of minutes, hours, days...
... so to speak the essence of life -- that is the sum of life, and the sum of life cannot be anything else.
That's why, now, I'd like to reminisce.
I remember very clearly the moment I first understood that I'm me, that is, that I'm separate from the rest of the world.
I have a photograph where I'm sitting on father's lap...
... it seemed, that until that minute, I felt a unity with him and the world. And then it was suddenly as if I contrasted myself with him, and with everything that was around me.
I think, from that moment, I saw in myself an individual, a person.
Before then, I grew (so to speak) according to my genes and my inborn template.
But from that moment, as soon as I found myself facing the world, it began to affect me.
And the innate in me gradually started to undergo changes, processing, polishing —
impacts of the outside world, of that big life that surrounded me.
In other words my experience, what I experienced, the situations I found myself in, choices I made, relationships I had with people...
... contained a large and ever-increasing element of the world that raged around me.
So I thought that by telling my life, I will tell not so much about myself,
because that idea seemed bizarre to me: what would I speak about myself for?
But to speak of myself as an organism that had absorbed elements of the surrounding life,
a complicated life, contradictory to the life of the surrounding world,
then that other, big life, passed through itself -- something objective -- can be experienced.
And perhaps, objectively, something valuable.
If art, say a movie, must carry a message --
a message for humanity -- and if every such testament should also have a message,
then I would like to formulate my "message" right away.
Most of all, I would like to impart that it's necessary to hope and to believe,
that even very bad situations can turn around.
I will show that in my, and then in Sima's and my life
many misfortunes turned into incredible, amazing happiness, richness,
I will try to emphasize this, to show that one needn't despair.
Because I know that these days there is much despair in people's souls.
And so, we must believe and hope, and gradually things can turn around.
I think that in the years when mother and father were alive,
almost all of Poltava (except downtown), with its magnificent provincial buildings, looked like this.
I imagine that my mother live in a little house just like this one.
I know they had a two-story house. The first floor was wooden, and the second was made of plaster.
A pharmacy occupied the first floor. It wasn't just a pharmacy,
as for some reason grandfather also sold toys there.
The pharmacy had a large toy department.
Grandfather was not only the owner of the pharmacy,
but was also a pharmacist, chemist, and was always preoccupied in the laboratory with some invention
— and he loved toys; he would order the latest toys from Europe and America.
It was said that people would come to Poltava all the way from Kiev to buy his toys.
Only the latest toys. He loved mechanical toys.
Secondly, grandfather also had a medal for "Rescuing the Drowned"
— he threw himself into the water and rescued someone.
And thirdly, grandfather was the leader of the Jewish Self-Defense Squad against pogroms.
Mother and father? That's a high-school romance.
Mother finished highschool in 1907.
Maria Danilovna, her last name -- Liberson.
They called her Mannie.
There exists a recording of her evening graduation ceremony.
Mother and her friends, Rebeccah and Millie, finished high-school,
and the boys finished Poltava Secondary
with emphasis on engineering and technology.
My father was called Ziama -- Zinobiy Yakovlevich Markovich.
He came from a poor Jewish family,
with something like eight or nine children.
He was the only one with higher education. The grandparents didn't ??? play a role there?
...And so that graduation date was celebrated,
and there is a recording of the wonderful/amazing, romantically sublime plans that they had for this/their life/lives.
They didn't separate — they were separated somehow. [different words for separate?] note: maybe we should replace pronouns with their antecedents more often?
After the pogromi, grandmother and -father immigrated to Palestina
and mother didn't return to Poltava any more.
After she left them [her parents?], she returned to search for father.
Whereas (?) father finished/graduated from the Saint Petersburg Mining Institute.
In 1907 or 1908, right after the devastations (?) of the first Russian Revolution of 1905
and that wave of pessimism that the youth grasped/caught hold of (?), especially in Saint Petersburg,
it was as if there were a suicide epidemics; there were mass suicides.
Young kids/guys didn't know what to do with their lives, with themselves (?).
It seemed like in this country, all the hopes, perspectives/prospects to a change or movement had been lost.
At this time my mother, who was a student at some sort of higher female courses,
published in two or three newspapers the following announcement/open letter:
"To all boys and girls who are lonely, come to my place:
every Thursday, from 5 pm, I will open the doors of my room.
Let's socialize together, drink tea and coffee, talk, be friends.
Perhaps, together it will be easier  than alone."
According to the morals and standards of that time, this was quite a courageous, weird act, and it did not pass unnoticed.
While reading Alexander Blok's letters, I saw a reference to this;
he mentioned the courageous and strong action of the student Maria Liberson.
I stumbled across it quite by accident,
And it was so strange and interesting to read: I saw that my mother tried to engage very early into a/some/some sort of great life.
She didn't live inside of her small circle,
but was open to  people, and that was, of course, very appealing to me/and of course I liked that very much.
World War I had started, father went to war, he was drafted.
And he got captured by Germans.
For almost four years he was in captivity,
that's why later he spoke German very well.
During the war, mother organized a kindergarten for Jewish children,
for the very poor, whose fathers were mobilized.
The first Jewish kindergarten.
She described it in her diaries, day by day she would write something about every child.
It was touching; I could hardly read it without tears,
because about some Moishes and Judiths, at first totally abstract/foreign to me,
she would write with so much love:
today he pronounced such and such word correctly,
and Judith molded for the first time some kind of donkey.
All that was fixed, and it all seemed to mother extremely important,
full of content, and thus the work in the kindergarten
(she had found two helpers/assistants)
looked like an exceptionally poetic occupation/work.
It was as if she grew/cultivated rare flowers out of them.
Every one was an individual exemplar, every one was watered with special water, in a special mode,
and so gradually, as I was reading her diary, these children were flourishing/blooming:
some could sing, some learned to dance,
some knew how to mold and read poetry.
Totally downtrodden, suppressed, they turned into small plantlets/seedlings that were lovingly brought up.
It captivated me.
When I started to read the diary, I saw mother in a different light.
Not in the everyday one; not the mother that asks when I come home,
whether I tied the scarf and whether I ate the cutlet
[maybe insert some very common food that "English speaking" people eat? e.g. maybe sausage would fit better?]
As a general rule, mother managed the household/kept house poorly,
mother just knew how to arrange celebrations/parties (?).
Like setting the table for a holiday (?), preparing something extraordinary,
certainly/of course writing the menu in verse -- as much as one wants.
Everyday life didn't interest her.
Father returned from captivity, as everyone else, toward the end of the war, in 1919.
Apparently there they finally connected their lives,
although I suspect that even before father joined the army,
they certainly already had some kind of romantic relationship.
And since father already joined some Jewish labour party,
that merged with the Communist party in 1917, when the communists came to power,
father found himself/became a member of the Bolshevik Party.
And right away, he got his first designation:
Head of Education Department in Smolensk.
Where father and mother moved, they received a room --
it was a cell in the Smolensky Monastery, where they lived, and where I was born.
When I was six months old, father was one of the few Bolsheviks with higher education,
and someway (I don't know how) he was acquainted to Anatoly Lunacharsky,
Lunacharsky summoned him to Moscow, and father became one of Lunacharsky's deputies in the Ministry of Education.
This is how we settled down in Sretensky Boulevard in a huge house,
with fifteen or sixteen rooms in one apartment,
twenty housewives in the kitchen and a tremendous fireplace in our room,
on top of which, as far as I can remember, there would be always drying doll heads that were moulded out of black bead:
During the whole Moscow period, and then also later, I was accompanied (?) by dolls.
Mother was passionate about puppet plays and wanted to create her own theatre.
Black bread was absolutely inedible, it was wet and slimy,
and mother used it like plasticine, like clay.
When I was three or four years old, I remember how father bought me a little white goat.
We went together to the market to buy cabbage, I saw a white goat and was stunned.
I started to beg, said that I didn't want to part with the goat.
I hugged it, that I remember very well: how I put my arms around it, and father couldn't resist.
And so we came to mother with a live/living/real? white goat.
The first night we put it under father's desk,
and I demanded to sleep next to it, hugging (?), under the same desk.
To the dismay/horror/consternation of our neighbors, for two or three days, the goat would be wandering from room to room --
and those were large, magnificent/luxurious apartments, apparently belonging to some pre-revolutionary rich people,
that were turned into horrible communal apartments; employees of the Ministry of Education lived there.
And so, fifteen to twenty rooms, but only one bathroom, one toilet and one kitchen --
and right the a goat appears to revive the situtation.
I remember myself crying when my parents gave it away to some kindergarten. I remember that well.
Strangely, I also remember how father sang when he was shaving in the mornings,
and for some reason mother would tell him: stop singing -- it's impossible to focus/concentrate.
At that time, mother was working in some preschool/day care centers (?) and was writing reports in the mornings.
And father would reply to her -- strange that those things stay in memory --
he'd say: I won't sing, and you will think one day: how sad that he doesn't sing any more,
it would be so good if he sang.
This I remember, this phrase: "it would be so good if he sang".
Another thing I remember is how we went sledding on Sretensky Boulevard,
I remember snow-covered Moscow, because later I wouldn't see snow any more, in Berlin there was no snow.
When in 1925 it was called (?)
that it's necessary to trade with the West, to buy cars and industrialize (do/engage in industrialization?) the country,
all higher-educated people, members of the party, were sent to work abroad.
And father, a certified (?) engineer who knew German fluently,
had to resign from the Ministry of Education and go to Berlin to work as a deputy of Nikolay Krestinsky,
who was a plenipotentiary/envoy (?) at that time.
This is how in 1925, we came to Berlin.
"Wenn du einst in spätern Jahren
dieses Büchlein wirst durchlesen,
denk daran wie froh wir waren,
als wir Kinder noch gewesen
und mit frohem, heitren Sinn
wanderten zur Schule hin."
"If you once, in many years, read this album again,
then remember, how we were young, joyful and cheerful (?), and how happily we went to school"
In my memory, Germany merged into one big kindergarten.
That was childhood.
I played with dolls, dreamed to have a doll stroller, which father fundamentally did not want to buy:
he bought a goat, but a doll stroller, as he found, was unworthy of a Soviet little girl,
too bourgeois.
During our life in Germany I turned into a German girl.
Because I went into a Polish school only in the first year,
and then I went to a normal German highschool (?), I learned to write Gothic letters,
I glibly read children books written in Gothic letters.
Gothic writing is very peculiar, and I thought I had forgotten it since then. But recently I found one book -- turned out I still can read it.
We had to sit putting our hands on the desk -- strict German highschool.
It was for girls only -- boys and girls studied separately at that time. There were intermissions (?), silly girly games... [this sentence is weird]
I liked school. I didn't have any negative emotions about it.
Everybody went somehow (?). All in all, at that time I wanted to be like everybody, to live like everybody, to merge with others (?).
In fact, that desire I had later as well, I will talk about it. ["talk about it" sounds too strict, can you think of another word?]
Every summer we would go somewhere.
To Salzburg, Paris -- I was seven when we went to Paris for the first time.
I remember how from Paris, for some reason, father went to Nice, to the Southern beach, and mother and I -- to Biarritz.
And in the post office, mother wrote him a letter that I can remember:
Из Москвы до Биаррица
Прилетела Лиля птицей
И, увидев Биарриц,
От восторга пала ниц.
Не сравнить хвоста синицы
С оперением жар-птицы,
Так бледнеет ваша Ниццац
Пред красою Биаррица.
Мой совет: пора решиться
С Ниццей вам скорей проститься,
Взяв билет до Биаррица.
Ваша Лиля-баловница.
Mother was full of humour, acting (?). She had a very strong game(?) element.
Say, out of some disgusting renting apartment somewhere in a hotel or anywhere
in a flash, she would create something special:
here she'd slip on a silk scarf, there she'd rearrange, move something,
she'd buy some  vase with flowers, and at once everything revived.
У нее был дар интерьера, желание видеть вокруг себя красивые вещи — и шутить.
Ну вот эпитафию такую, скажем, написала:
Умру, стихов останется тетрадка.
Заглянешь в них когда-нибудь украдкой
и скажешь: «Все же был родной котяга
(я маму почему-то звала кошкой, котягой)
...Все же был родной котяга,
слегка — поэт, в душе — большой бродяга,
лирически мяукал он и прочее
и вместо точек ставил многоточие.
И потом помню, как мы пошли на вокзал и приехал папа к нам в Биарриц, какая это была радость.
Море, скалы, прекрасная беззаботная радостная жизнь.
Это была жизнь как у всех.
Все куда-то уезжали летом, все потом рассказывали друг другу, где они были...
И этому наступил конец.
Всегда мы ездили на каникулы или в Швейцарию, или во Францию. Куда-нибудь.
А тут папа решил в свой отпуск поехать в Россию,
посмотреть, как работают машины, которые он покупал.
Мама его уговаривала не ехать.
Она как-то боялась. Мама вообще боялась советской России,
и в дальнейшем это скажется на нашей судьбе.
Раздался телефонный звонок, и какой-то человек попросил свидания с папой.
Папа хотел узнать, кто это, человек ответил:
«Я должен остаться для вас инкогнито».
Папа отказался с ним встречаться.
Через два дня он снова позвонил и сказал, что «речь идет о благополучии и жизни вашей семьи».
Ну, папа с ним встретился в кафе после этого.
И тот человек, русский, папе не знакомый, не назвавшись, сказал:
«Вы не должны ехать в Россию, вас оттуда назад не выпустят».